Guide to the Buildings, Grounds and Landmarks in New Haven Photographs
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Buildings, grounds and landmarks in New Haven photographs
1653-1970
RU 685
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
15.25
The materials consist of maps, photographs, engravings, drawings, slides, and lithographs of New Haven, Connecticut scenes, residences, buildings, and landmarks. The bulk of The materials consist of photographs of New Haven and surrounding environs from 1860-1930s. Included are aerial views, scenes of the New Haven Green, photographs of streets, and various individual residences. Of particular interest are the snapshots of houses used for tax purposes, or as documentation of the structure before demolition.
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 48-A (YRG 48-A), Yale pictorial records and collections.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and subsequent accessions. I. Photographs. II. Oversize. III. Folio.
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of maps, photographs, engravings, drawings, slides, and lithographs of New Haven, Connecticut scenes, residences, buildings, and landmarks. The bulk of The materials consist of photographs of New Haven and surrounding environs from 1860-1930s. Included are aerial views, scenes of the New Haven Green, photographs of streets, and various individual residences. Of particular interest are the snapshots of houses used for tax purposes, or as documentation of the structure before demolition.
Architecture, Domestic -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Buildings -- Connecticut -- New Haven; East Rock Park (New Haven, Conn.); Hamden (Conn.); New Haven (Conn.) -- Pictorial works; Drawings (visual works); Maps (documents); Photographs; Slides (photographs)
- Photographs, Series I
  - General: maps (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    See also: box 29, folder 94
  - General views (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - New Haven harbor (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - New Haven As It Is (book) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aerial views
    - 1800s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - New Haven, Mill River, and Lake Whitney from East Rock, 1800s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1920s (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Hindenburg over New Haven: May 6, 1937" (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - New Haven Map Project
      - 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
    - Transparency, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Academy Street--General William H. Russell's Collegiate and Commercial Institute (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alden Avenue (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Armory Street (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bishop Street (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Blake Street (Hamden) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bradley Street--Grove Cottage School (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Broadway, pre-1960s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Broadway, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brookside Drive (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Camp Trumbull (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Canner Street (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Center Street (West Haven) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Chapel Street
    See also: box 13, folder 1
    - 1870-1890 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
    - Before the Princeton game, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Corner of Church Street (Box 2, Folder 29)
      General
      See also: box 6, folder 134
    - Corner of College (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - North (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Buildings (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - New Haven House/Hotel--corner of College (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Beers Tavern--site of Hotel Taft, 1653-1850 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Proposed plan for Chapel Square Mall, circa 1950s (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Hyperion Theatre (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Park House (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Roger Sherman House--corner of High Street (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Church Street (Box 2, Folder 39)
    See also: box 13, folder 3
    - Corner of Elm Street (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "Bijou Theatre" property #26 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - City Hall and County Courthouse (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
    - Old New Haven Post Office (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Tontine Hotel (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Cold Spring Street (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - College Street
    - circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - North, 1865, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
    - North from Chapel Street (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - North from Chapel, showing State House (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - North (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - North from Chapel Street (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - North from Crown Street (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - South, 1872, 1880s (Box 3, Folder 55-57)
    - South from Elm Street, 1880 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Corner of Elm Street (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Corner of Grove Street (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Corner of Wall Street (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Rev. Claudius Herrick house (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Rialto Theatre, fire (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Columbus Avenue (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Congress Avenue (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Congress Avenue--Congress Square (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Cottage Street (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Crown Street (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Derby-New Haven border toll gate (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Dixwell Avenue (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Dwight Street (Box 4, Folder 71-72)
  - East Street--corner of Greene street (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - East Rock, general (Box 4, Folder 74-75)
    - Camp Putnam (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Farnam Drive (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - Orange Street (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - Soldier's Monument (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - Warren photos (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - J. F. Weir painting (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - circa 1865 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - circa 1870 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - circa 1874 (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - circa 1875 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - circa 1887 (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Dedication of Soldier's Monument, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - circa 1880s (Box 4, Folder 88)
    - circa 1900s (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - East Rock Road (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Edgehill Road (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Edgewood Terrace (Westville) (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Edgewood Terrace (Westville)--home of D. G. Mitchell (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Edwards Street (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Elm Street
    See also: box 13, folder 4
    - East views, circa 1860-1890 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - post-1900 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Corner of College Street (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Corner of High Street (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Various views (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Corner of York Street (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - DeForest House (#51) (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Nathan Smith House (#57), or Miss Edwards' School for Girls (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Bristol House (#65) (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Brewster House (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Corner of Church Street (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Governor Eaton's house between Church and State Streets (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Methodist church (#97) (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Christ Church (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Whitlock's Bookstore (#219) (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Properties #397-399; #969-971 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Everit Street (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Filbert Street (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Fort Nathan Hale (Box 5, Folder 113)
    See also: box 13, folder 5
  - Franklin Street (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Frontage Road (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - George Street (#363) (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Gill Street--Walter Camp house (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Grand Avenue (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - The Green
    See also: box 13, folder 6
    - 18th century drawings (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Second (post 1700) and Third (post 1757) meeting houses (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Undated views, circa 1780-1845 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - circa 1830 (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Barber Views
      - 1831, 1840, 1851, 1860-1865 (Box 5, Folder 123-126)
    - Warren photographs, 1862-1863 (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - 1874-1876 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - 1870s-1880s (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - 1887 view (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - 1890s (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - 1900-circa 1920 (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - 1920-present (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - Franklin Elm--corner of Church and Chapel Streets (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - Regicide's Tomb (Dixwell Monument) (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - Old State House (Box 6, Folder 136-137)
      See also: box 2, folder 26-27 See also: box 2, folder 39 See also: box 2, folder 46 See also: box 4, folder 95 See also: box 9, folder 210 See also: box 9, folder 212-215 See also: box 29, folder 94
  - Greene Street (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - Grove Street (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - Various views (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Old New Haven Arena (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Graves-Tilston house (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - Old New Haven Colony Historical Society (Box 6, Folder 142)
  - Grove Street Cemetery (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - Hamilton Park (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - The Harbor (Box 7, Folder 145)
    See also: box 1, folder 2 See also: box 1, folder 5 See also: box 29, folder 94
  - High Street
    - North (Box 7, Folder 146)
    - Various views (Box 7, Folder 147)
    - near Grove Street (Box 7, Folder 148)
    - North from Library Street (Box 7, Folder 149)
    - from Wall Street (Box 7, Folder 150)
    - Houses (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Highland Street (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Hillhouse Avenue
    - Various views (Box 7, Folder 153)
    - A. N. Skinner house (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Hotchkiss family (Box 7, Folder 155)
  - St. Mary's Church (Box 7, Folder 156)
  - Hospital, New Haven
    - Howard Avenue (Box 7, Folder 157)
    - Raleigh Fitkin Memorial Unit (Box 7, Folder 158)
    - Horse-drawn ambulance, circa 1900 (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - Hospital, Yale-New Haven--aerial views (Box 7, Folder 160)
  - Hospital, New Haven and Yale-New Haven--misc. interiors (Box 7, Folder 161)
  - Howe Street (Box 7, Folder 162)
  - Hudson Street (Box 7, Folder 163)
  - Huntington Street (Box 7, Folder 164)
  - Lake Place (Box 7, Folder 165)
  - Lake Saltonstall
    - 1874, 1876, circa 1887 (Box 7, Folder 167-169)
    - 1896, Undated (Box 8, Folder 170-171)
  - Lake Whitney (Box 8, Folder 172)
    See also: box 10, folder 242
  - Lake Wintergreen (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - Lake Wintergreen, Wintergreen Falls (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - Laurel Road (Box 8, Folder 175)
  - Lighthouse Point (Box 8, Folder 176)
  - Linden Street (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - Livingston Street (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Long Wharf (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - Loomis Place (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - McKinley Avenue (Box 8, Folder 181)
  - Maple Street (Box 8, Folder 182)
  - Meadow Street (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - Morris Cove--Shoreham Hotel (Box 8, Folder 184)
  - Mount Carmel (Sleeping Giant) (Box 8, Folder 185)
  - Norton Street (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Orange Street (Box 8, Folder 187)
  - Park Street (Box 8, Folder 188)
  - Poplar Street (Box 8, Folder 189)
  - Prospect Street (Box 8, Folder 190-192)
  - Putnam Avenue (Box 8, Folder 193)
  - Quinnipiac River (Box 8, Folder 194)
    See also: box 1, folder 5
  - Ralston Avenue (Box 8, Folder 195)
  - Rogers Road (Box 8, Folder 196)
  - Sachem Street (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - St. John Street (Box 9, Folder 198)
  - St. Ronan Street (Box 9, Folder 199)
  - St. Ronan Terrace (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Savin Rock (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Savin Rock Point (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Savin Rock--photos by L. E. Tuttle (Box 9, Folder 203)
  - Savin Rock Hotel (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Savin Rock--residence (Box 9, Folder 205)
  - Shelton Avenue (Box 9, Folder 206)
  - Sherland Avenue (Box 9, Folder 207)
  - State Street (Box 9, Folder 208)
  - State Street--Bradley House (Box 9, Folder 209)
  - State House, German copper cut print, circa 1830 (Box 9, Folder 210)
  - Sugarloaf Mountain tunnel (Box 9, Folder 211)
  - Temple Street
    See also: box 13, folder 16-17 See also: box 29, folder 94
    - North from Chapel
      - 1860s, 1870s, 1880s, 1890s (Box 9, Folder 212-215)
      - undated (Box 9, Folder 216)
    - Corner of Grove Street (Box 9, Folder 217)
    - Properties #432-444 (Box 9, Folder 218)
    - Churches (Box 9, Folder 219)
    - Site of Timothy Dwight College (Box 9, Folder 220)
    - Center Church (Box 9, Folder 221-222)
    - Gerry house (Box 10, Folder 223)
    - Louis Lunch, Temple and Grove Streets, circa 1960s (Box 10, Folder 224)
    - Sanford house (Box 10, Folder 225)
    - Temple Music (Box 10, Folder 226)
    - Trinity Church (Box 10, Folder 227)
    - United Church (Box 10, Folder 228)
    - Noah Webster house (Box 10, Folder 229)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10, Folder 230)
  - Trumbull Street (Box 10, Folder 231)
  - Tweed-New Haven Airport (Box 10, Folder 232)
  - Union Street (no longer extant) (Box 10, Folder 233)
  - Wall Street (Box 10, Folder 234)
  - Water Street--Benedict Arnold house (Box 10, Folder 235)
  - Water Street--Pavilion Hotel (Box 10, Folder 236)
  - West Rock (Box 10, Folder 237)
  - West Rock--Judges' Cave (Box 10, Folder 238)
  - West Rock Avenue (Box 10, Folder 239)
  - Whitney Avenue (Box 10, Folder 240)
  - Whitney Terrace (Box 10, Folder 241)
  - Whitneyville area
    - Lake Whitney (Box 10, Folder 242)
    - Whitney Armory (Box 10, Folder 243)
    - Eli Whitney Mill (Box 10, Folder 244)
  - Willow Street (Box 10, Folder 245)
  - Winchester Avenue (Box 10, Folder 246)
  - Wooster Square (Box 10, Folder 247)
  - York Square--Tower Parkway (Box 10, Folder 248)
  - York Street (Box 11, Folder 249)
  - York Street properties (Box 11, Folder 250)
  - Miscellaneous
    - New Haven Gas Co. employees (Box 11, Folder 251)
    - Panoramic views (Box 11, Folder 252)
    - Points of interest (Box 11, Folder 253)
    - History, monuments, etc. (Box 11, Folder 254)
    - Surrounding areas (Box 11, Folder 255)
    - Unidentified (Box 11, Folder 256-259)
- Oversize, Series II
  - Albertus Magnus College, Rosary Library, Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - 1927 Calender Illustrations (Studdard Engraving)/Showing: College Street 1872, Green in the 70's, "New Haven Today", Old Campus and Stale House (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - 505 College--The Atwater Block (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Church St--Court House (North Wing City Hall), Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - 51 Elm--Deforest House Interiors (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Fort Hale, 1843, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - The Green, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Groups (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Houses
    - Between High and York (house) (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - 80 High St., Undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - 238 York St., 1920 (or prior to) (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified, 1904, undated (Box 12, Folder 12-13)
    - 83 Grove--Miss Montfirt School (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - St. John's Church (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Views
    - Church Street Looking North (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Temple Street between Chapel and Elm, 1860, undated (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Temple Street at the Green (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - George Street Corner of York, Webster School, undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Slides and Transparencies (Box 13)
- Folio, Series III
  Scope and Contents
  Folders with asterisks(*) contain ten or more items
  - Drawing of New Haven harbor (Folder DR29F94)
  - Historical map of New Haven, 1934 (Folder DR29F94)
  - 455 Chapel Street--the New Haven Hotel (Folder DR29F94)
  - 151-155 Church Street (Folder DR29F94)
  - College Street from the south (Folder DR29F94)
  - Elm Street
    - from south with historical notes, 1908 (Folder DR29F94)
    - St. Thomas Church (Folder DR29F94)
  - New Haven Green
    - watercolor (Folder DR29F94)
    - eastern view (Folder DR29F94)
    - Connecticut State House, 1840 (Folder DR29F94)
  - Temple Street
    - from south--engraving (*) (Folder DR153F104)
    - from south (Folder DR153F104)
    - Center Church (Folder DR30F95)
    - signed etching by Louis Orr (Folder DR30F95)
    - undated (Folder DR30F95)
    - Wooster Square (Folder DR30F95)
    - historical map, 1880 (Folder DR30F95)
- Glass slides of Yale and New Haven, Circa 1875; Accession 2002-A-182
  - Glass slides of Yale and New Haven, Circa 1875 (Box 1, Box 1A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Due to the physical nature of the material in box 1 of Accession 2002-A-182, staff supervision is required.
- Mounted photographs of Yale and New Haven, circa 1875; Accession 2003-A-081
  Received from estate of Edward L. Whittemore.
  - Mounted photographs of Yale and New Haven, circa 1875 (Box 1)